NIL-55A, Malviya Nagar, New Delhi-17

Mobile: +91-9958241190 Email: suritabasu@gmail.com

surita basu@yahoo.com

Dr. Surita Basu



CAREER SUMMARY

I completed my PhD, thesis titled as "Study of miniaturization of surface patterns and self-organization of carbonaceous nanoparticles on soft thin films and their applications" under the supervision of Dr. Jayati Sarkar from Department of Chemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi. Surface patterns and surface modifications in thin polymeric film with/without nanoparticles are of great demand in high end technologies like functional coatings, tissue engineering, electronics and others. These surface patterns created by self-assembly technique are affordable, convenient and economically viable method to create patterns on thin film. My experience with industrial R&D and QC&QA for 5 years after B.Tech has backed me with rich experience in the academics.

EDUCATION			
Degree	Institute	CGPA/%	Year
PhD.	Chemical Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, NewDelhi-110016	7.9	2015-2021
M.Tech	Nanoscience & Technology, Guru Gobind Singh Inderprastha University, Delhi-110078	82.84	2012-2014
B.Tech	Polymer Science & Technology, Calcutta University, Kolkata-700009	76.53	2002-2005
B. Sc	Chemistry, Calcutta University, Kolkata-700014	60.53	1999-2002
H.S	St. John Diocessan Girls HS School, Kolkata-700029	66.4	1997-1999

PUBLICATIONS		
Paper	Surita Basu, Bhukhya Vishnu Naik, Kalluri Ankarao, Prabir Patra, and Jayati Sarkar. Dewetting assisted	
published in	self-assembly of graphene nanoparticles by diverse approaches. Bulletin of Materials Science volume	
journals	(2021) 44:236	
	Surita Basu, Bhukhya Vishnu Naik, Kalluri Ankarao, Prabir Patra, and Jayati Sarkar. Self-assembly of	
	graphene nano-particles on biocompatible polymer through dewetting. Surfaces and Interfaces. (2021)	
	9:101009	
	• Surita Basu and Jayati Sarkar. "Selective adsorption of oil on self-organized surface patterns formed over	
	soft thin PDMS films." Chemical Engineering Science 207 (2019): 970-979.	
	Surita Basu and Jayati Sarkar. "Miniaturization of surface patterns in soft elastic film over patterned	
	substrates." Chemical Engineering Science 197 (2019): 195-203.	
	• Jeevan Jyoti,, Surita Basu, Bhanu Pratap Singh, and S. R. Dhakate. "Superior mechanical and electrical	
	properties of multiwall carbon nanotube reinforced acrylonitrile butadiene styrene high performance	
	composites." Composites Part B: Engineering 83 (2015): 58-65.	
Paper	 7TH International Conference on Smart Materials & Nanotechnology, Webinar, 20-21 July 2020, Nano Ring Formation of MWCNT by Dewetting of Thin Film, Surita Basu, Prabir Patra, Jayati Sarkar. 	

presented in conferences	• International Conference Nano-M&D 2019, in Paestum, Italy from 4-8 June 2019, Influence of graphene particles on morphology and patterns on dewetting of thin polystyrene film, Surita Basu, Bhukya Vishnu Naik, Kalluri Ankarao, Prabir Patra, Jayati Sarkar.
	 23rd Polish Conference on Chemical and Process Engineering- 23rd PCCandPE, in Jachranka-Warszawa, Poland, from 2-5 June 2019, Selective adsorption of oil from oil-water mixture on the instability driven interfacial surface patterns over thin soft PDMS film, Surita Basu and Jayati Sarkar. International Conference on Advance Materials (ICAM 2019), March 06-07, 2019, Jamia Millia Islamia, Delhi, Influence of graphene on morphology and patterns on dewetting of thin polymeric film, S. Basu, B. V. Naik, K. Ankarao, P. Patra and J. Sarkar
	• 3rd International Conference on Soft Materials , December 09-14,2018, Malviya National stitute of Technology, Jaipur, Effect of graphene nanoparticles embedded in thin film, S. Basu, B. V. Naik, K. Ankarao, P. Patra and J. Sarkar
	 Soft Matter: Young Investigators Meet 2018, May 23 – 25, 2018, Koti Resorts Shimla, Selective adsorption of oil on interfacial surface patterns over soft thin PDMS film, S. Basu and J. Sarkar International Conference on Sculptured Thin Films, March 30-31, 2018, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Delhi, Adsorption of oil on surface patterns on thin elastic film, S. Basu and J. Sarkar Industry Day, September 23, 2017, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Delhi, Oil adsorption on surface patterns, S. Basu and J. Sarkar. NanoIndia Conference, March 15-16, 2017, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi, Miniaturization of surface patterns, S. Basu and J. Sarkar International Conference ComFlu @HYD, December 12-14,2016, International Institute of Information Technology, Hyderabad, Miniaturization of surface patterns over patterned substrate, S. Basu and J. Sarkar Seventh National Level Annual Research Symposium of Chemical Engineering Research Scholars, Chemference 2016, December 3-4, 2016, Indian Institute of Technology Gandhinagar, Gandhinagar, Miniscule pattern formation over patterned substrate, S. Basu and J. Sarkar.
Workshop attended	 Short course on Surface area and Porous material characterization, March 12, 2019, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi. Workshop on Polymer Science and Technology, December 9, 2019 at Malviya National Institute of Technology, Jaipur. Workshop on Advance Characterization Workshop on 3D Atom Probe Tomography, December 18-19, 2017, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi.

EXPERIENCE			
Work	Worked with S. Chand Technologies Pvt. Ltd. from September 2009 to July 2010 as Subject Matter		
experience	Expert.		
	Worked with Monochem Graphics Pvt. Ltd. from February 2008 to August 2009 as Sr. Engineer QA&		
	QC.		
	Worked with STP Ltd. from June 2007 to December 2007 as Assistant Manager Marketing.		
	Worked with ICI India Ltd. from June 2005 to May, 2007 as Technical Officer R&D.		

SKILLS		
Skills	Research and Analysis and Problem Solving	
	Written and Oral Communication	
	Research and Project Management	
	Self-Management & Collaboration	

ACHIEVEMENTS		
Projects	Major Project on "Synthesis of MWCNT and reduced graphene oxide based acrylonitrile butadiene	
	styrene composites and its application in electromagnetic interference" from CSIR-NPL as a part of	
	M.Tech project.	
	Minor Project on "Graphene-bismuth ferrite nano-composite as a photo catalyst" as a part of M.Tech	
	project.	
	Summer project on "Synthesis of polyaniline nanoparticle using polyether amine as stabilizer" from	
	Calcutta University as a part of M.Tech.	
	 Certification and implementation of ISO/TS 16949:2002 in Monochem Graphics Pvt. Ltd. 	
	Developed "Lead and chromate free paints" in auto refinish range for ICI paints.	
Awards and	Research Excellence Travel Grant (2019) from Indian Institute of Technology Delhi.	
Certificates	• CSIR Travel Grant for International travel (10472) in June 2019.	
	Certified Internal Auditor for ISO 9001:2000.	
	Certified Internal Auditor for ISO/TS 16949:2002.	

PERSONAL INFORMATION		
DOB	• 04.09.1980	
Marital	Married	
Status		
Children	One Daughter	
Father's and		
Mother's	Tapan Kumar Basu	
Name		
Husband's	Bhabani Basu	
Name	Deepak Barua	

REFERENCES

Dr. Bhanu Pratap Singh

Principal Scientist and Deputy Head Advanced Carbon Products and Metrology Section CSIR-National Physical Laboratory

Dr. K.S. Krishnan Road, New Delhi 110 012

bps@nplindia.org

+91-11-4560 8426

Prof. Anindya Datta

Professor

Room No: BFR-206

Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University Sector - 16C, Dwarka, New Delhi - 110078 (India)

<u>anindya.datta@ipu.ac.in</u> +91-11-4560 8426